Guide to the Mosess (Moe) Fishman Papers ALBA.224
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Mosess (Moe) Fishman Papers
1937-2008
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Fishman, Mosess (Moe), 1916-2007
ALBA.224
6 Linear Feet in 10 manuscript boxes, 6 card boxes, and one oversize flat box
23 Cassettes (8) 60 mins., (9) 90 mins., (1) 120 mins., (4) unmarked
8.418 Gigabytes in 440 computer files
Mosess (Moe) Fishman fought in the Spanish Civil War with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade and served as Secretary-Treasurer of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB). This collection consists of organizational records, correspondence, clippings, photographs (analog and born-digital), audiocassettes, and videos from his service and activities with VALB.
Biographical Note
Mosess (Moe) Fishman was born in New York City in 1915. He graduated from Stuyvesant High School in New York City and enrolled in City College, but did not finish college for financial reasons. He later worked in a laundry and driving a truck.
Fishman joined the Young Communist League and became involved in anti-fascist activity in the mid-1930s. In 1937 he volunteered to fight in Spain with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, taking part in the Brunete offensive, where he was severely wounded when a sniper's bullet shattered his thigh. He spent the next three years in and out of hospitals in Spain and the U.S. He had recovered sufficiently to serve in the Merchant Marine in World War II. After the War he returned to New York and became active in aiding Spanish refugees. In 1951, he took over as Secretary-Treasurer (later Secretary) of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) when the organization was labeled "subversive" by the Attorney General's office. After a strenuous legal battle, the label was removed in the 1970s. He remained a political activist and kept his post with VALB until his death in 2007.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of paper and born-digital material accumulated by Moe Fishman during his many years as Secretary of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. It includes incoming correspondence from Lincoln Brigade veterans and others, among them representatives of veterans' organizations in Spain and elsewhere in Europe. Also included are clippings, pamphlets, memorabilia and photographs (many of them related to gatherings of Spanish Civil War veterans), letters written by Fishman to Howard Lederer during his service in Spain, and some family papers. Also in the collection is a small body of papers and photographs belonging to Lincoln Brigade veteran, Court Bevensee; these were entrusted to Fishman at the time of Bevensee's death. Document types include correspondence, publicity items, organizational records and reports, clippings and photocopies of clippings, popular publications and article reprints, photographs, videos, and audio recordings of interviews, events, and musical performances.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged in loose chronological order by document type or format.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Most of these materials were included in Brandeis University Library's transfer of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives to New York University. Some later items came from the creator and Georgia Wever, a member of VALB and friend of Fishman.
Related Materials
For more information about Moe Fishman, ALBA, and VALB, see the Moe Fishman Memorial Exhibit, ALBA.EXHIBITS.001; Moses (Moe) Fishman Videos, ALBA.VIDEO.003; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Records, ALBA.019.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade
- Moe Fishman personal documents, VALB records: XV Anniversary of Spanish Republic - Records of Service in the International Brigades, 1915-1996 (Box 1)
- VALB records: Volunteers who Liberated Spain, bequest documents, Instituto Beni Cultwali Bologna, Salvador Dali Museum, SIPTU Conference report, Refugi Antiaeri de la Placeta Macia, 1980-2002 (Box 2)
- VALB records: Amicale des Anciens Internes Politiques et Resistants, International Brigade Memorial Trust, Bill Van Felix video and audio tapes lists, Spain Trip, Ebro Battle 65th Anniversary, Memorial events, 2002-2008 (Box 3)
- VALB records: A Celebration of Chuck Hall's LIfe, 2005; TW_ALBA_224_ER_2 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_ALBA_224_ER_2)
- VALB records: Memorial Day, 2005 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_ALBA_224_ER_3)
- VALB records: Ebro, 2005 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_ALBA_224_ER_5)
- VALB/ALBA, 2007 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_ALBA_224_ER_6)
- VALB records: No jubilem la memoria Presenta, A Pinch of Priorat Memories, 2007 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_ALBA_224_ER_7)
- Court Bevensee records and correspondence, 1910-1997 (Box 4)
- Correspondence: Howard Lederer, Fred Schofs, Roy Hendrickson, Nate and Corine Thornton, C. Brooks, Moe Fishman, others, 1937-2008 (Box 5)
- Clippings, photocopies, 1974-2008 (Box 6)
- Publications, 1963-2004 (Box 7)
- Photographs, 1937-2009 (Box 8)
- Photographs: Moe Fishman at office, Jessica W. et al at Tamiment Library, 2003-2004 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_ALBA_224_ER_1)
- Photographs: SF Monument dedication, 2008 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_ALBA_224_ER_8)
- Photographs: SF Monument, 2008 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_ALBA_224_ER_9)
- Plaques, 1972-2005 (Box 9)
- Textiles: hat, t-shirt, flag, undated (Box 10)
- Memorabilia: seal, medals, pin, 1936-1986 (Box 11, Box 16)
- Index cards: "Veterans dead and missing in Spain", undated (Box 12)
- Index address cards, undated (Box 13)
- Audiocassettes: interviews, musical performances, anniversary events, 1982-1999 (Box 14, Box 15)
- Oversize graphics, 1937-2007 (Box 16)
- Physical digital media carriers (Box Shared Tamiment 056)